The violence of our time is caused by obedience.
Throughout American history, the political leaders have always exhorted the American
people to be nice and quiet and leave things to them.
But when very serious evils confronted the American people, they had to go beyond the
congressmen and the senators, and they had to commit civil disobedience, and they had
even to break the law.
And the abolitionists had to do it, and right here in Boston, they had to violate federal
law by trying to bring a slave away from the federal marshals, they had to commit civil
disobedience, the labor movement had to do this, they had to violate the law, they had
to disrupt things, they had to do all sorts of impolite things, they had to sit-ins of
sit-down strikes of 1936 and 1937, and only this finally brought that modicum of justice
that the labor movement demanded, and the civil rights movement went through the same thing.
And you know that Congress did not act on the civil rights laws of 64 and 65 until blacks
went out into the streets and made a commotion.
They did not do it on the basis of some polite discourse.
We have been brought up to believe that the American political system works beautifully,
it is democratic, Congress represents us, the president is elected, he represents us, it
doesn't work that way.
Democracy depends on people speaking out, and in times of great crisis, on people creating
a commotion.